This video is sponsored by
本期视频由Skillshare
Skillshare
赞助播出
Okay, before I show you the actual footage from the movie...
在我揭开这部电影的真面目之前
(Trust me, it looks nothing like the thumbnail)
（电影长得跟海报一点都不像！）
Let me show you the end credits, first
我们先来看看这部电影的制作人员名单
Yes, the credits.
对，人员名单
I have a problem with the credits
我对人员名单有意见
Because, you see
怎么说呢
This movie's credits...
这部电影的名单
Are RIPPED from another movie!
是从另一部电影里抄过来的！
Just with slight alterations to each person's name
每个人名字就改一个字
Even the credits are a knock-off!
连人员名单都是山寨的！
Makes sense, though
不过细想也合理
Because there is no way in hell that THIS MOVIE...
毕竟啊，这种画质
Has THIS many artists behind it
特么怎么可能有这么大的团队
That's the god damn movie, people!
对，这就是电影画面
Just soak it all in!
忽然精神爽快了有没有！
This is The Autobots
这是《汽车人总动员》
Yes, it's actually called that
行不改名坐不改姓
And it is, in my opinion, the most shameless Chinese movie ever made
在我看来，它是中国电影有史以来最无耻的电影了
The English title rips-off the Transformers
英文名抄袭《变形金刚》
The Chinese title and character design copy Cars, of Pixar Studio fame
中文名和角色设计抄袭皮克斯工作室的《赛车总动员》
Part of the title is covered up
海报上的“人”字还被故意遮挡
Just so it looks even closer to the Pixar title
让名字看起来更接近皮克斯作品
The fact that the poster bears more resemblance to Cars 2's poster
海报和《赛车总动员2》的海报雷同度之高
Than the actual film itself
让电影本身自愧不如
Makes the intention very clear
电影意图也不言而喻
Like many egregious cases of Chinese knock-offs
和中国内地很多无耻的山寨货一样
This movie was mocked around the world
这部作品被世界各地媒体疯狂嘲笑
CNN from the US reported on it
CNN跟踪报道
SET News from Taiwan made fun of it
台湾三立新闻公然取笑
Nippon TV from Japan investigated it
日本电视台也进行了调查
But, there is one place where the reaction is often overlooked, at least in the west...
但是有一个地方，常常被大家忽略...
How did Chinese filmgoers react to this?
中国电影观众，对此又有何反应？
"There's a good meme on the internet"
“网上有句话说得好“
"The cleanest water has no fish"
“水至清则无鱼”
"The cheapest person has no shame"
“人至贱则无敌”
Today, let me tell you the story of The Autobots
今天，我们一起来看看《汽车人总动员》
From its on-screen hilarity
了解一下电影本身
To behind-the-scenes drama
谈谈电影背后的争议
And yes, to domestic audience reception
再聊聊内地观众的反响
Let me help you make sense of this madness
让我来梳理一下这诡异作品
And also, peer into the side of Chinese pop culture you don't often hear about
带同大家窥视中国流行文化
This is the most shameless Chinese movie
这是中国电影史上最无耻的
Ever made
山寨作品
THE MOST SHAMELESS CHINESE KNOCK-OFF
（最无耻的中国山寨电影）
CHAPTER ONE
（第一章）
The story tells a 9-year-old... engineer?
故事主角是一个9岁的……工程师（？）
Who wants to make the coolest, most badass smart car ever
他想要制造一辆最帅、最霸气侧漏的智能汽车
But ends up making 3 cars, each with its own personality flaws
但最后却造出3辆怪胎，每个怪胎都有不同缺点
K1 is too restless
K1过于好动
(And also flirtatious for some godforsaken reason)
（而且还十分……骚）
Behold, the most annoying character introduction of all time
接下来请欣赏影史上最烦人的角色介绍对白
"Call me K1!"
“叫我K1！”
"Uhh... 1 as in number one!"
“呃……一是第一的一！”
"Ahoo, I'm number one!"
“啊吼，我是第一！”
"Yeah! I'm the champion, number one!"
“耶！我是冠军，第一冠军！”
"Number one champion!"
“第一冠军！”
"Yahoo!"
“雅虎！”
Does anyone feel dirty after that?
是不是觉得菊花一紧？
I feel like I will be charged 6 dollars per minute
电话上听这种对白
For hearing that voice on a phone
收费每分钟十块钱
Anyway, K2 is too rigid in programing
接下来，K2性格太死板
"Sorry, master"
“对不起，主人”
"Please give me a precise coordinate"
“请给个具体坐标”
"Which direction, for how many meters"
“往哪个方向，前进多少米”
Simone Giertz would be proud
你是Simone Giertz造出来的吗！？
K3...
K3 ......
I think he's supposed to be lazy
导演大概觉得它是懒
But he looks more like he's drugged up the ass
我觉得它是嗑丸了
I would too, if I was in this movie
我要是被困在这部电影里我也吸毒
"Why doesn't K3 move?"
“K3怎么一动也不动呢？”
"Oh~ Right?
“哦〜是呀“
"He should open his eyes"
”它应该张开双眼”
"Run towards us"
“跑到我们身边”
"And play with me in the lab"
“然后跟着我一起在实验室里玩儿”
Oh my god, this horny car needs to calm the f**k down
草泥马，这辆咸湿车快去洗冷水澡
"Dadadada, dadada"
“哒哒哒哒，哒哒哒”
Anyway, after their completion
搞完车车
The four decide to participate in a racing championship
四个智障决定一起参加大奖赛
In hopes of winning the coveted poop-shaped trophy
以大便奖座为目标
Thus begins a long and treacherously boring journey of training
于是，大家开始了一场枯燥又无聊的训练之旅
And by training, I mean none of that
啊对不起，没有训练
Bad weather? Upgrade
天气不好？升级系统
Potholes? Upgrade
路上有坑？升级系统
Need someone to do chores? Upgrade
要做家务？升级系统
Got sick?
生病了？
"I'm so sick.
“我好难受“
Can you bring me home?"
“你和我回去吧”
Someone should neuter this oversized Lovense Lush
孩子们，请阉割你的巨型跳蛋宠物
Finally, the big day came
最后，大赛开始
And all of their hard works paid off
大家的努力也得到了回报
Cannonballs? Weather shield upgrade
天降炮弹？开启天气护盾
Potholes? Suspension upgrade
路上有坑？开启避震系统
Traps? Household chore upgrade
前方陷阱？开启家务系统
And most importantly
到最后
With each other's help, they overcome their flaws
三辆智障互相扶持
Cheered on by all 4 audience members
在全场四名观众的欢呼之下
In an epic slow-motion finale
他们一个慢动作
They win
成功夺冠
And the movie just immediately ends
然后电影就瞬间结束
Yep, 20 seconds after they cross the finish line
对，冲线二十秒
Credits
结束！
Oh well, at least it has a finale
哎，算了，好歹也是有个结尾
SPONSOR MESSAGE
（赞助信息）
In our video about Mulan, I made fun of the animators
我们之前一期视频里，我嘲讽了《花木兰》的特效
For creating a shoddy looking phoenix
说里面做凤凰画面的动画师
And tell them to sign up for Skillshare
应该上Skillshare进修一下
God, I wish I saved that joke for this video instead
早知道我就把那个梗留到这个视频里了
Skillshare is an online learning community
Skillshare是一个在线学习社区
With thousands of inspiring classes for creative and curious people
有着上千门趣味创意课程
For the director of this film
这部电影的导演应该看一下
I recommend "Character Design Crash Course: Dynamic Design in Four Steps"
“角色设计速成班：动态设计的四步骤”
A beginner course for emerging cartoonists to come up with
这门课程专门叫初学者如何设计
*cough cough*
*咳*
ORIGINAL DESIGNS OF THEIR OWN!
原！创！角！色！
Other class topics include writing
其他课程包括写作
Editing
剪接
Compositing
合成
And animation
和动画
Classes are concise, ad-free, and affordable
课程简短无广告，而且十分便宜
Less than ten dollars a month with an annual subscription
一年订阅，每月不到十美元
The first 1000 people to use the link in my description
前1000个点击下方链接的观众
Will get a free trial of Skillshare Premium Membership
可以立刻免费试用Skillshare
So you can explore your creativity
马上开始探索自己的创意
All jokes aside, we all want 2021 to be a better year
说真的，我们都希望2021年能过得好一些
And one of the best way to make the year better
而让这一年变好的最佳方式
Is to make yourself better
就是让自己变得更好
So, for real, I really do recommend giving Skillshare a try
所以，我真的很推荐大家去Skillshare
Especially their workshops, which encourage you to create something
一起参与Workshops活动
The most important thing is to get started, right?
敢于尝试才有进步，对吧？
So, what are you waiting for?
那你还在犹豫什么呢？
CHAPTER TWO
（第二章）
In a previous video of mine
之前一期视频里
I called Pure Hearts the worst Chinese movie ever made
我说《纯洁心灵》是中国影史上最烂电影
While, visually, The Autobots is god awful
视觉上，《汽车人总动员》确实惊人
I still think that Pure Heart is the worse of the two
不过我还是觉得《纯洁心灵》更烂一点
Mainly because The Autobots is at least coherent
《汽车人》剧情至少是连贯的
But also, it isn't actually a movie
而且，《汽车人》本质上也不是电影
Not really
不全是
The Autobots was a TV animation
《汽车人》本来是电视作品
And like many other cheap toddlers shows around the world
和世界各地的廉价儿童电视动画一样
No one really gives a sh*t about it
一般没人鸟
It also helps that the animation is so poorly made
再说这部电影画面炸裂成这样
It takes a second for you to realize who they are copying
很多人估计没反应过来这电影在抄谁
The show was later stitched together into a feature film
这个节目后来才活生生被剪接成电影
And pushed into theatres for a quick buck
扔到电影院里骗钱
The controversy didn't start until the theatrical poster came out
电影海报的出现，才是争议的源头
Which, in a way, is more of a knock off than the movie itself
这海报啊，比电影本身抄得还狠
This similarity is, of course, immediately noticed by everyone
这种相似性立即引起所有人的注意
Nippon TV contacted the director for a comment
日本电视台对导演进行了电话采访
To which the director denied all accusations
导演否认了所有指控
Claiming it is just... learning from Disney
声称这只是...向迪斯尼学习
And this is where the crapshoot begins
这下子就炸锅了
Understandably, Chinese social media users sided with Nippon TV on this
这下，中国网民们与日本电视台站在了同一阵线
Unlike Pure Hearts, which was mostly mocked and made fun of
《纯洁心灵》最多只是被嘲笑
Reviews for The Autobots were mostly of anger and frustration
《汽车人》那是被大家骂得体无完肤
Many called it shameful
很多人说电影不要脸
Some wished Pixar would sue them
有人希望皮克斯能告他们
In response, the director accused critics of being, quote...
导演在微博上反骂大家，说大家是……
"A New Generation of Traitors"
“新时代的汉奸”
Siding with "foreigners" instead of "supporting Chinese animation"
与外国人一起欺负中国动画
And blamed everyone for the film's poor box office return
觉得大家拖累了电影的票房
If you know about Disney
迪斯尼大佬
The number one rule is, you do not piss off Disney
我们都知道，得罪不起
And, as you would expect, the Autobots got sued
正如所料，《汽车人》被起诉
Facing a lawsuit, the director has the gall to claim that
面对诉讼，导演居然有脸说
The Autobots is an independent creation
《汽车人》是独立创作作品
And accused Disney of abusing the legal system
并指责迪斯尼妨碍司法公正
While in the middle of a lawsuit
官司打到一半
The director announced a sequel
导演公布了《汽车人总动员2》
Which never materialized
幸好没了下文
Thank f**k
卧槽好险
And the kicker is, this film was pushed out allegedly as a way
而最搞笑的是，这部电影其实当初很可能就是
For the director to exploit a loophole in government fundings
为了骗取政府补贴才强行剪接出来的
With its production company based in Xiamen
作品的影视公司位于厦门
A city with media production fund programs
厦门有政府影视补贴
This film is eligible for 255 thousand Yuan
这部电影的片场应该能得到25万元
Or about 39 thousand US dollars in funding
约3.9万美元的政府补贴
It's probably more than enough to recoup the production cost and then some
这估计已经是电影成本的好几倍了
In the end, Disney won the lawsuit
最后，迪斯尼胜诉
What else do you expect?
意外不意外
The news was reported by Mtime, one of China's largest cinema network
中国最大影视网页“时光网”对此进行了报道
Their headline?
新闻标题：
"REJOICE!
“喜大普奔！”
'The Autobots' Ruled As Copyright Infringement"
“《汽车人总动员》被判侵权”
What a sh*t show
哎呀我爆米花吃完了
CHAPTER THREE
（第三章）
Do you know Genshin Impact?
你听过《原神》没？
Yeah it's one of those games that came out
对，就是最近刚出来
Riding the success of Breath of the Wild
被指抄袭《旷野之息》的游戏
I suspect a lot of people didn't realize that this is a Chinese made game
很多人似乎没意识到，《原神》其实是一部中国游戏
Since "made in China" has a very negative connotation
毕竟“ 中国制造 ”四个字已经是贬义词了
The developer is likely aware of this, too
开发商可能也意识到这个问题
Which is why this game has its title in Japanese instead of Chinese
所以《原神》的英文标题是日语读音，而不是汉语读音
Anyway, the reception of the game is...
游戏的风评嘛……
"Wait, what the f**k"
“等等，这……“
"SHE'S SO CUTE!"
“她好特马可爱啊！”
... generally positive
……还是不错的
After all, games that copy other games are nothing new
毕竟游戏互相模仿也不是什么新鲜事了
Ubisoft just released their own take on the same formula
育碧最近也发行了同类型的游戏
And gamers are okay with it, as long as the product is good
只要产品不错，游戏玩家也是可以接受
But there is one place that really hates this game...
不过，有这么一个市场却很讨厌这个游戏
China
中国市场
Now, you probably noticed that I haven't been very neutral in this video
你可能意识到，这期视频我的态度并不客观
That's because I, along with so many other Chinese artists and viewers
这是因为我和很多中国的艺术从业者和观众一样
Am not only angry at this film
不仅讨厌这部电影
But the entire industry of Chinese knock offs
更是讨厌中国的山寨工业
And that's a side of the story you don't often hear about
而这个故事，踏出内地就没有多少人知道了
Mockbusters are not exclusively a Chinese phenomenon
山寨电影并不是中国独有现象
Far from it
各地都有
Yet, when you hear the word knock-offs
然而，当您听到“山寨”一词
Your thoughts, and my thoughts, are almost always the same
你和我的想法几乎都一样
"Of course it's China"
“又是中国”
It is the equivalent of hearing news of an anti-mask protest
换位思考，大家听到反口罩示威新闻时，第一反应也都是
And going "of course it's America"
“又是美国”
As an American, you know it's not your fault
作为美国人，你知道你自己没错
And you dislike these people just as much
你也一样不喜欢这群反口罩的示威者
But it frustrates you that THAT is what your fellow people are doing
但每次有人提起这群人，你依然会觉得沮丧
And this is why Chinese filmgoers would rather side with the media that make fun of China
这就是为什么中国影迷情愿和嘲笑中国的媒体一边站
Than stand with the film that represents the worst of the Chinese creative industry
也不愿意支持这部中国山寨工业的杰作
Chinese people, especially the urban, middle class, educated people
中国民众，尤其是中产阶级、受过高等教育的年轻城市市民
Are increasingly frustrated with Chinese knock offs
对中国仿冒品越来越痛恨
Partly due to this international perception
其一部分原因便源自这种国际舆论
At the risk of sounding overly sensitive
这话说起来有点矫情
Here is a personal example
不过我还是想分享一个个人例子
To this day, people still comment under our Chinese sword video with the same joke
发布两年，大家依然在我们的“中国剑”视频下给一样的留言
Why are Chinese swords not as famous?
为什么中国剑不出名？
"Because they were made in China"
“因为是中国制造的呀”
It's so normalized, people don't think it is an insult anymore
这句话如此深入人心，大家都不觉得自己在骂人
Despite the subtext being "nothing good comes from China"
尽管其潜台词是“中国造不出好东西”
And if something good is made in China
如果中国制造了好东西
It will not be recognized as such
那就没人会意识到它是中国作品
Even by its own creators
连创作人都不敢承认
But the main reason for our hatred
但我们痛恨山寨的主要原因
Is just that, we are tired of seeing cheaters win
还是因为我们看到太多事业有成的抄袭者了
Guo Jingming, one of the most famous young writers in China
郭敬明，中国最有名的年轻作家之一
Plagiarized most of his famous works
其大部分作品都被指抄袭
He was sued in 2003 by fellow writer Zhuang Yu, whose work was plagiarized by Guo
2003年，郭敬明因抄袭作家庄羽作品被起诉
Guo lost the lawsuit, but refused to apologize
郭敬明输了官司，但拒绝道歉
He went on to become a director, writing and directing the notoriously bad "Tiny Times" series
他后来成为导演，拍出了人人喊打的《小时代》系列
With the first film alone grossing 484 million Yuan
光第一部电影票房就以4500万元的预算
Against its 45 million Yuan budget
收入4.84亿人民币的票
Similarly, Chinese screenwriter Yu Zheng was sued by famous author Chiung Yao for plagiarism
同样，中国名编剧于正，因抄袭被名作家琼瑶告上法庭
He lost the case
他输了官司
Yet, he remains one of the most prolific screenwriters in the industry
却照样成为中国内地最当红的编剧
And this sh*tty film grossed nearly 5 million Yuan
而这部屎烂片票房居然有五百万人民币
Although the production company claims it has a 10 million Yuan budget
虽然制片商号称有一千万成本
I doubt that's the case
我还真不信！
The public's frustration reached a boiling point recently
终于，前不久，公众对抄袭的痛恨情绪达到了沸点
On December 31st, 2020
2020年12月31日
15 years after Guo losing the case
郭敬明败诉整整15年后
He and Yu Zheng finally apologized publically
终于和于正一起公开道歉了
Why?
为什么呢？
Because just 9 days earlier
因为道歉的九天前
Over 156 media personnel cosigned an open letter, calling for the boycott of plagiarists
超过156名影视人员共同签署了一封公开信，呼吁抵制抄袭者
In which these two buttwipes were named specifically
信中特别点名了这两个冚家铲
Almost immediately, Yu Zheng is edited out of a variety show he appeared in
不到几天，《我就是演员》果断把于正从节目中剪掉
And a new show he wrote is now postponed
而他编剧的新节目也被无限期延迟了
It seemed like justice is finally being served
正义似乎得到了伸张
The comments under their apologies are not acceptance
但大家对他们道歉，给予的不是接受
It's not even rejoicing
也不是欣喜
Some expressed relief
有人感到慰藉
Most are still angry
大部分人依然愤怒
And now you know why Chinese people find this movie so infuriating
现在你明白为什么中国观众们这么讨厌这部电影了
CONCLUSION
（结论）
I hate The Autobots
我讨厌《汽车人总动员》
And so do people in China
中国的电影观众亦然
Because it stands as the most glaring symptom
因为它是中国创意工业
Of the rotten core within the Chinese creative industry
败絮其中的典型例子
An industry where it pays to be a cheater
我们讨厌这个作弊者能登顶的工业
There are so many artists in China
中国有无数艺术从业者
Especially animators, who choose a life a hardship
尤其是动画师，甘心贫困
Just to have a chance of pushing the Chinese animation industry forward
只为推动中国动画产业尽微薄之力
The director of Ne Zha graduated med school
《哪吒》的导演于医科大学毕业
Yet, instead of becoming a doctor
但却放弃从医
He decided to go into animation, self-taught
选择自学动画
Because he loves the industry and wants to help make it better
只因为他热爱动画行业，希望能助其崛起
He spent 3 years crafting his debut short film while living in poverty
他花了3年时间，在清贫的生活中打造自己的动画作品
He couldn't even afford Internet at home
他穷到家里连网线都没有
If he needed to go online, he had to go to his friend's house
要上网，还得去朋友家
Yet you're telling me this creatively bankrupted f**kface is the most popular writer in China
你好意思告诉我这个只会抄袭的扑街仔却成为了中国最出名的作家？
And this horny car made it into the theatres?
这辆饥渴卡丁车还有脸进入大屏幕？
Luckily, both the audience and the industry are changing
幸好，观众和行业都在发生变化
Ne Zha eventually became the highest-grossing animated film in China
《哪吒》成为了中国票房最高的动画电影
Original films are being valued more and more
原创作品也越来越备受重视
While copycats, even high-quality ones, are being called out
而山寨货，哪怕山寨得好，也被大家拒之门外
I sincerely hope the notoriety of The Autobots is a sign of change
我真心希望《汽车人总动员》的臭名，意味着时代的转变
That cheaters are being kicked out
抄袭着被唾弃
That the truly passionate artists are finally getting the spotlight
大家把灯光聚在真正有创作热情的艺术家身上
Perhaps one day
也许有一天
China can shed away the knock-off label
中国可以摆脱山寨之名
And produce something truly loved by people around the world
能做出惊艳世界的作品
And hopefully, next time
也希望下一次
They don't have to hide behind a Japanese name
我们的作品不用披上日文名字